Dewa
Tendou Shougi
Town
参りました
I lose.
では　約束どおり
Then as promised, you will fight the 7th generation Kyotouryuu head, Yasuri Shichika, with Outou Nokogiri on the line.
ここにいる虚刀流七代目鑢七花と
「王刀·鋸」を懸けて勝負していただこうか
はい
Yes.
Kiguchi Zanki
There are limits to how much you can look down on someone!
人をバカにするのも 大概にしていただきたい
A swordsman can't fight without a sword!
剣士が刀なしで戦えるわけがないでしょう
Or are you telling me to wield my sword against an opponent who bears neither armor nor weapons?
それともわたしに　防具も着けず刀も持たぬ者を相手に
剣を振るえというのですか
This is an affront to the Shinou Issou school!
これこそ心王一鞘流を侮辱している
とがめ
Togame...
Shichika! Shichika!
七花　七花
Huh?
えっ　あの
What...
Outou
Nokogiri
Saw,
the King
Note: Dewa Tendou Shougi Town
It's October, and Autumn is well under way.
長月　秋も深まってまいりました
ここ　出羽天童将棋村は 将棋の聖地と呼ばれる地でございます
This is the so-called Shougi sanctuary, Dewa Tendou Shougi town.
四季崎記紀の変体刀　「王刀·鋸」を求めて
In order to obtain Shikizaki Kiki's Deviant Blade Outou Nokogiri for their sword collection journey,
the strategian Togame and the 7th generation Kyotouryuu head, Yasuri Shichika, have come to this town.
この地を訪れた　奇策士とがめと虚刀流七代目当主鑢七花
早々に　刀の持ち主
They quickly entered negotiations with the 12th generation head of the Shinou Issou school, Kiguchi Zanki.
心王一鞘流十二代目当主 汽口慚愧との交渉に当たったのですが
However, it ended in failure.
失敗に終わっております
Sorry.
ごめん
とがめは将棋戦で汽口を倒したのに
You beat her at Shougi, but I went and blundered...
俺が足を引っ張っちゃって
そなた 本当に剣が使えぬのだな
You really can't use swords, can you?
Yeah...
What's the reasoning behind it?
どういう理屈なのだ
I agree with Kiguchi in finding it hard to believe that you become weaker when you wield a weapon.
汽口の言うとおり
武器を持って　弱くなるというのは考えられんぞ
It's true that it sounds like nothing but an excuse.
言い訳と思われても仕方ない
I can't explain it.
俺には　説明できない
What now then?
さて　どうしたものか
Now we're at a stalemate.
これはこれで手詰まりだ
でもさ　何だろう
Though, I did notice something...
四季崎記紀の刀の毒に当てられてるとは思えない真っすぐさだよな
Kiguchi seems too pure to be under the effects of the poison of Shikizaki's Deviant Blades.
汽口は
She might not be.
当てられておらぬのかな
ひょっとすると　それが「王刀·鋸」の特性なのかもしれぬな
In fact, that might be the focus of Outou Nokogiri.
うん　それってどれだよ
What do you mean?
I mean, it's the one Shikizaki Kiki sword that doesn't carry Shikizaki Kiki's poison.
だから「四季崎の刀の毒を持たぬ四季崎の刀であることが」だ
砕いて言うなら　毒気のなさこそが王の証しとでも言うのか
To put it simply, its lack of poison is proof of kingship.
仮に　防具なしの無刀　反則なしで汽口と対峙していたら
For example, were you to face Kiguchi fair and square without having to use armor or weapons, do you think you could win?
果たして　そなたは勝利を収めることができておったか
うーん　分からない
I don't know...
ただ　言えることは汽口にはすきがないって思ったよ
I can only say that she felt very cautious to me.
Kind of like a taut rope.
まるで張り詰めた糸だった
I guess her "aura" felt very sharp.
気迫っていうのか　そういうのはひしひしと感じられたぜ
あれくらいまじめに剣の道に励んでる人間ってのは
I think that's the first time I've seen someone with such a strict zeal for the sword arts.
初めて見た気がする
これまで戦った相手の中じゃ
She's probably one of the better opponents I've fought so far.
それなりの上位に食い込むことになるだろうな
ちぇりおー
Cheerio!!
Geez...
Ow!
ったく
痛っ
Why are you admiring the opponent you lost to so much?
負けた相手に感心してどうするのだ
Right...
なあ　とがめ
Hey, Togame...
錆のときや姉ちゃんのとき 日和号のときみたいによ
Don't you have some plan, like with Sabi or Nee-chan or Biyorigou?
何かいい作戦はないのか
Well as far as the actual fighting aspect of plans go, I know very little.
作戦と言われてもな
基本的にわたしは戦闘そのものについては門外漢だ
現に薩摩で　「賊刀·鎧」の収集に当たったとき
Like how my plan to pierce Kanara's armor failed in Satsuma when we went to get Zokutou Yoroi.
わたしの提案した鎧通しは 校倉必には通用しなかったわけだしな
Oh right, I remember that.
ああ　そんなこともあったっけ
大体　錆のときや七実のとき　日和号のときに立てたわたしの奇策は
In the first place, the schemes I used against Sabi, Nanami, and Biyorigou all relied on your strength and skills.
あくまでもそなたの強度と練度が前提だ
そなたが弱体化しておるなどという余計な条件があっては
If you were to become weaker, even I wouldn't be able to think of a solution.
さしものわたしも打つ手がない
A solution, huh...
打つ手ねぇ
あっ　汽口の将棋の腕前の方は　どうだったんだ
How were Kiguchi's shougi skills?
She was pretty good, I guess.
まあ　そこそこだ
剣の道を選ばず 将棋一本に絞りこんでおれば
If she had devoted herself to shougi instead of the path of the sword, she'd be truly formidable.
かなりの使い手になったであろう
I wouldn't even be a match for her.
わたしなど 相手にならぬほどのな
Wow, she must be pretty good for you to praise her.
へー そこまで言うんだ
とがめも褒めてるじゃん
褒めてはいない
I'm not praising her!
鳳凰から「次の刀は天童だ」と聞いたとき
When Houou said the next one's in Tendou, I figured it'd be this dojo.
あの道場だと思った
But I didn't know the head had changed.
だが　当主は代わっていたな
孫娘が継いでおったのか
The granddaughter succeeded the position...
I see...
そうか　最近当主になったのか
She only recently became the head?
She's around the same age as you too.
年齢はそなたと同じくらいかな
So around 24, 25?
ってことは　２４ ２５か
ふーん もうちょっと若く見えなくもなかったけれど
I would've thought she was younger, but I can't really tell women's ages.
女の年はよく分からんな
フンッ まあそなたはそうであろうよ
Well, I guess that's natural for you.
とがめが俺より年下だってことは分かるんだが
I do know you're younger than me though.
Cheerio!
ちぇりお
誰が童子属性だ　誰が
Who are you saying looks like a child?!
I didn't say anything like that...
いや　そんなことは一言も言ってないが
I'll admit it's true that I look quite a bit younger after your sister cut my hair though.
そなたの姉に髪を切られてしまったせいで
ますます幼く見えるようになってしまったことは認めるが
You didn't have to go out of your way to say that...
そんなことわざわざ認めなくてもいいよ
And didn't you say you liked my hair this way?
そなたこそ　この髪が気に入っておるのではないか
Well? Well?
どうだ　ほれほれ
Uh...
いや　その
Excuse me.
失礼します
W-What's the matter, Kiguchi-dono?
どっ　どうしたのだ汽口殿
とがめ殿 先ほどの勝負なのですが
Togame-dono, about the match earlier...
あっ　うむ
Y-Yeah?
やはり　不公平があったように思うのです
I've come to believe it was unfair.
とがめ殿と七花殿が帰られてから
After you left, I also gave it some thought.
わたしも考えてみたのですが
七花殿があそこまで弱かった
Given that Shichika-dono was that weak...
It couldn't really be called a proper fight.
となれば　これは勝負が成立したとはいえません
不公平があったように思うのです
I think it was unfair.
I wish to correct that injustice.
不公平は是正されねばなりません
And so I propose that Shichika-dono studies at the Shinou Issou school under my direct tutelage,
よって　七花殿をわが心王一鞘流の門下生として迎え入れた上で
このわたしが直々に鍛え上げ
and after training there, face me again in a fair fight.
その後あらためて 正々堂々の対戦
What do you think?
ということでいかがでしょうか
It's around here?
こんな所にあるのかい
あっ　あっ　はい
Y-Yes...
あっ　あそこ　です
It's o-over there.
Dokutou Mekki
So this is Dokutou Mekki...
これが「毒刀·鍍」ですか
No doubt about it.
間違いない
川獺の左腕もそういっている
Kawauso's left hand also agrees.
It's so pristine even in this harsh environment...
こっ　こんな環境の悪い所で　よく
It has survived without any rust or corrosion...
さびもせず　朽ちもせずに
保存されていたものですね
I think this is actually the perfect environment.
逆に良い環境だったのかもしれぬぞ
保存ではなく　封印されておったのかもしれんということだ
It's not that it was preserved so much as sealed.
実際その状態のときは斯様な禍々しさを外に発してはいなかったからな
Because of this environment, its ominous aura was kept from leaking outside.
まっ　その辺りは四季崎記紀の刀ということなのであろうよ
Well, I suppose that's typical of a Shikizaki Kiki blade.
一応言っておくが鴛鴦
Just as a warning Oshidori, don't try to draw this sword.
この刀　抜こうと思うなよ
はい
Understood.
あっ　あのう
A-As a swordsman, if Umigame had been able to see this...
刀を武器とする海亀さんが　これを見られたら
Indeed, what would he have thought?
ええ　どう思ったでしょうね
Indeed.
Sword training...
剣の修行か
虚刀流が刀を持つなんて
Kyotouryuu wielding a sword?
Imagine if Dad or Nee-chan got wind of this.
親父や姉ちゃんが聞いたらなぁ
But what's involved in sword training?
でも　剣の修行って何するんだろう
I've never been trained by anyone other than Dad.
親父以外に手ほどき受けたことないからな　俺
You sound like you're complaining about it, but why do you have that huge smile on your face?
と　さっきから愚痴っぽいことを並べておるわりには
なぜに顔がほころんでおるのだ
Eh? I'm not smiling...
えっ いや　そんなことないけどな
You always get like this whenever you spot a woman!
ったく　女と見ればすぐこれだ
Huh?
She can teach you all you want about how to use your body!
精々手取り足取り教えてもらうがいいわ
Huh? What?
えっ　何　どうしたの
What's wrong Togame?
とがめと
がめさん
Togame-san?
でもちょっとヤバいな 今回は
This could be bad though...
ヤバいどころか　最悪だ
Bad? This is the worst!
あれは己が不利になることは許せても
She's the kind of person who refuses to accept a handicap on her opponent, even if she has one.
相手が不利になることは許せないという性格だ
But fighting without armor is an advantage to me, not a hindrance.
いや　防具なしは
俺には不利じゃなくて有利だろ
You couldn't explain that to her though!
それが　説明できなかっただろう
Yeah...
たまにいるのだよ ああいう人間が
I guess there are people like that around.
わたしのように知謀策略を巡らすことにしか興味のない人間には
She's an enigma to someone like me who knows nothing but devising genius strategies.
理解に苦しむところだがな
だからこそ策も通じぬ
That's why my plans won't work.
心の鬼を心で斬ると書いて慚愧
The name Zanki is written as "Slay your heart's demon with your heart".
わたしの見るところ一筋縄ではいかんよ
I can't use my ordinary methods.
十二代目　汽口慚愧は真人間過ぎる
Kiguchi is far too honest and upright.
Upright, huh...
真人間か
Going to the extent she has makes her almost inhuman.
あそこまで行きついてしまうと 逆に人間らしからぬ存在だな
心王一鞘流の道場から門下生がいなくなった理由も
I kind of understand now why the Shinou Issou dojo no longer has any students.
何となく分かろうというものだ
かといって
さて　行くか
Time to go then.
あれ　とがめは行かないのか
Huh? You're not coming?
What would be the point of me going?
わたしが行ってどうする
I was thinking you'd watch me practice...
稽古を見ないのかなって
I'd just be a distraction if I were there.
わたしがいるとそなたも気が散るであろう
Not in the slightest.
いや　全然
Besides, I need time to work on my own plans!
それにわたしは 策を練るのに忙しい身だ
I guess that's true.
それも　そうだな
I'm off then!
じゃあ　行ってくる
You didn't even put up a fight!
あっさりし過ぎだー
もう一押ししろー
Try harder!!
Huh? Was I too early?
あれ　早過ぎたかな
いえ もう稽古は始まっております
No, training has already started.
Please use that cloth over there.
そこにあるぞうきんをお使いください
七花殿　まずは道場を清め
Shichika-dono, we begin by cleansing the dojo in order to prepare a refreshing space for us to train in the martial arts.
すがすがしい空間を整えることから 武芸の道は始まります
O-Okay...
Answer with "yes!"
返事は　「はい」と
堅苦しいことを申し上げて恐縮ですが
You may be uncomfortable with formalities, but starting today, you are training in the school of Shinou Issou as my student.
本日ただ今より
七花殿はわが心王一鞘流の門下生となりました
You must act as such.
そのおつもりで
Yes!
はい
All right!
よし
七花め　初稽古を心細く思っているであろう
Shichika's probably feeling lonely since this is his first training session.
I should show up and surprise him.
ここはわたしがいきなり行って 励ましてやらねばな
That'll be enough for the cleaning.
さて　掃除はこれでよしとしましょう
That was a good morning sweat.
朝からいい汗をかいたな
Shichika-dono, don't move.
七花殿　動かないで
Shichik—
七花
とがめ殿
Togame-dono?
Togame?
とがめ
Why's she running away like that?
何　あんなに慌ててるんだ
This was on your hair.
これが髪に付いておりました
Oh...
おっ　おう
Do not kill it.
殺生はなりません
This school is not one of slaying.
わが流派は殺人剣にあらず
I-It's none of my business!
か　関係ない
It's nothing!
別に　どうってことない
No, no!
違う　違う
No!!
違うったらー
では　始めるといたしましょう
Let us begin then.
よしっ
All right!
First is the swing.
まずは 素振りです
One!
Two!
Wha—
Three!
Four!
遅い
He's late!
I'm back!
今 帰ったぞ
あれ　もう寝てんのか
Huh? Going to bed already?
いやー　疲れたなぁ
Man, I'm tired...
しかし　何だな
I've got to say, swordsmanship is a lot harder than I thought...
想像以上に剣の道は険しいし
それにも増して厳しいな　汽口は
And Kiguchi sure is strict.
でも　それが嫌じゃない
I kind of like it though.
Oh? And how do you like it?
ほう どう嫌じゃないと
So you were awake?
起きてたの
Well, well...
That's quite the turnaround from when you told me you hated swords.
あれほど剣を持つことを拒んでいたそなたの変わりようったら
I'm shocked!
びっくりするわ
No, it still feels wrong to me to wield a sword as a Kyotouryuu.
いや　虚刀流が刀を持つことには今でも抵抗があることに変わりはない
でも対戦相手の俺に あんなに厳しく手ほどきをしてくれる汽口が
It's just that Kiguchi is giving me such strict training despite being her opponent...
Oh really?
Strict training? I wonder what kind.
手ほどきとは何の手ほどきやら
Well, today was upper swings...
今日はな　こう上段の素振りをな
Oh really?
Is that so?
そうだったかな
Huh?
えっ あっ そういえばとがめ今日道場に来てなかったか
Oh right, didn't you come by the dojo today?
I thought—
確か
I didn't!!
行ってない
えっ　だって
But...
You mistook someone else!
人違いだ
いや　その格好そうやたらに
But that figure was definitely—
I'm tired! I'm going to bed!
疲れたもう寝る
何怒ってんだ
What's she mad about?
One!
Two!
Three!
Bath?
風呂
稽古で風呂
Practice in the bath?
いや　修行
No, training?
荒行
Discipline? Waterfall?
滝
乾布摩擦
Towel rubdown?
Nooo!!
Shichika-dono, here.
七花殿　これを
Ah, thanks.
はい
では
Now then...
I'm back.
ただいま
Man, that was rough.
いやー　参った参った
あの心王一鞘流ってなかなかすごいらしいぞ　とがめ
That Shinou Issou stuff is pretty amazing, Togame.
It's a "sword of life".
活人剣といってな
It's a school that exists only for the pursuit of the way of the sword, abstaining from conflict.
無用な争いを好まず
ただ剣のみを追究する流派なんだそうだ
殺人剣にあらず まさに虫も殺さずだ
It's so different from the killing schools that it even disapproves of squashing bugs.
I guess it's kind of like the complete opposite of Kyotouryuu.
まあ　言ったらそこは虚刀流とは真逆ってことになるんだけどな
とがめ
Togame?
Food.
食事
Huh? You haven't eaten yet?
あれ まだ食べてなかったのか
Don't tell me you were waiting for me?
もしかして俺のこと待ってた
うん　遅過ぎるぞ
You're so late.
Sorry, I already ate with Kiguchi—
すまん　俺　汽口んとこで夕飯ごちそうになっ　て
So you can't eat anymore after having dinner with her?
汽口と食事したからもう食べないと
そなたのことを待っていたのだぞ
I was waiting for you!
いや　違う
Wait, that's not it—
What's not it?!
何が違うのだ
いつからあの女と膝つき合わせて食事をする仲になったのだ
When did you get so close to that woman that you can eat dinner by her side?!
No, that's not it!
いや　そうじゃなくて
The training was so rigorous that I got so hungry I couldn't move anymore!
あまりに稽古が激しくて 俺 腹が減って動けなくなったから
汽口が見かねて
Kiguchi couldn't stand the sight, so...
ふん
I'll eat this too, of course!
もちろん これは食べる
I would never turn down dinner with you!
とがめと一緒に 決まってるじゃん
And the food Kiguchi served was kind of frugal, so I didn't really get full on it.
いや　汽口のところの食事は何というか
すごく質素で 全然腹の足しにならなかった
Still, you could have gone ahead and eaten without me.
でも　先に食べててくれてよかったんだぞ
It doesn't taste good eating alone.
１人で食べてもおいしくない
Nothing!
何でもない
So, how was today's training?
で　剣の修行は どうだった
It was pretty rough.
いや　なかなか大変だ
道のりはかなり険しくて長い
The learning curve is pretty steep...
いや　汽口がさ
But Kiguchi is really—
That's enough!
もうよい　まずは食事だ
Food first!
Huh? Didn't you bring the topic up?
って　えっ とがめが話題振ったんじゃ
Let's eat!
いただきます
Thanks for the food...
Good morning.
おはようございます
Good morning!
Is this good enough?
このくらいでよろしいですか
Yep!
Woah.
Keep your focus ahead of you.
視線はもっと真っすぐ
はい
Yes!
腰をもっと落とす
Drop your hips more.
はい
Yes!
Shichika-dono.
七花殿　ちょっとよろしいか
Stop for a moment.
Drop your hips just this far.
腰は　ここまで落とす
Okay.
Now walk forward like that.
そのまま前へ
すまん
Sorry.
いえ
It's okay, you've gotten better at footwork.
すり足は良くなってきました
今の要領をお忘れなく
Remember these essentials.
はい
Yes.
さて　お昼にしましょう
Now, how about we have lunch?
Shichika and Kiguchi were...
七花と 汽口が
No way...
そんな
まさか
Huh?
あれ 何　わたし
What's this?
何で　涙が
Why am I... crying?
What's happening?
何だろう
どうしてなんだろう
How did it come to this?
To think time could pass this slowly when you're alone...
１人でいる時間がこれほどまでに長く感じるとは
もういかん　いかん
No good, no good!
とがめー　ちぇりおー
Togame! Cheerio!!
I'm off to train!
稽古　行ってきます
Oh? You seem quite happy.
ほー　いやに楽しそうだな
Is training that fun?
そんなに修行が面白いのか
Actually, it's been almost ten days and I haven't really made any progress.
それがさ
もう十日近くになるが 実際何一つ進歩はしてない
So it would seem.
のようだな
How do you know?
何で分かるんだ
I can tell just by looking at you!
そ そなたの様子を見ておれば分かる
I don't even need to see you doing it!
じ　実際に見てなくても
But now I enjoy going to the dojo, like you said I would.
だが　とがめの言うとおり
道場通いは楽しくなってきたぞ
まあ　得手不得手にかかわらず
And in spite of how badly I'm doing, moving my body feels good.
体を動かすのは気持ちいいもんだ
Cheerio!!
ちぇりおー
Good work, Shichika-dono.
お疲れさまです　七花殿
Thanks.
ありがとう
It's already been ten days since we began, huh?
もう稽古始めて十日か
There must be something wrong with my teaching method.
きっと　わたしの教え方が悪いのでしょう
The truth is you're actually my first student.
実をいえば わたしは門下生を持つのは初めてなもので
色々と不格好なところもあるのでしょうが
I'm sure I'm lacking in various ways as a teacher,
but I can't do anything about it except ask you to bear with it.
そこは　我慢していただくしかありません
That's not true...
いや　そんな
I've got to say,
それより　俺が今まで会ってきた変体刀の所有者とは
you're different from any of the other Deviant Blade masters I've met.
あんた違うな
I'm sure that's not true.
そんなことはないでしょう
If I consider what's best for the nation,
天下国家のためを思えば
とがめ殿にこの王刀を手渡すのが一番正しいのだと分かっていながら
I'm aware that handing over Outou to Togame-dono would be the best thing to do.
どうしても私心を捨てられない未熟者こそがわたしです
But even knowing that, I still can't part with it out of my own amateur selfishness.
天下国家のため　ねえ
For the sake of the nation, huh...
But I'd like you to understand.
しかし　分かっていただきたい
これは道場の看板であると同時に 自身の証明でもあるのです
This both represents the dojo and proves my identity.
It's been passed down from generation to generation,
代々当主に受け継がれているということだったけど
旧将軍の刀狩令の折にはどうしてたんだ
but what happened during General Kyuu's sword hunt?
心王一鞘流は どうやってそのそれを 旧将軍から守りきったんだ
How did the Shinou Issou school keep it from him?
During that period, Outou Nokogiri had not yet come under the ownership of Shinou Issou.
その時代には
「王刀·鋸」はわが心王一鞘流の所有物ではありませんでしたので
If I recall correctly, it was the 8th generation Shinou Issou head who first took possession of Outou Nokogiri.
確か 「王刀·鋸」を心王一鞘流に持ち込んだのは
八代目当主だったと記憶しております
Your grandfather's grandfather's grandfather's grandfather?
あんたのお爺ちゃんのお爺ちゃんのお爺ちゃんのお爺ちゃんくらいか
No.
いえ わたしと先代とは 確かに孫と祖父の関係ですが
While it's true that I'm the granddaughter of the previous head, the Shinou Issou school is not one of blood inheritance.
基本的に心王一鞘流は
血縁によって受け継がれる流派ではありませんから
Is that right?
そうなんだ 虚刀流とは違うんだ
That's different from Kyotouryuu.
じゃあ八代目がどうして王刀を持っていたのかということは
So does that mean you don't know any details about how the 8th generation head obtained Outou?
はっきりとは分からないのか
I do not.
分かりません はっきりどころか まるで皆目
In fact, I don't have the slightest clue.
It wasn't as long ago as the sword hunt, but it's still a very old story.
刀狩令のころほどではないとはいえ
かなり昔のこととなりますので
I am an amateur.
わたしは未熟者です
そりゃあ　さっきも聞いたけど
You said that earlier...
I'm an amateur now, but in the past you couldn't even call me that.
今もそうですが
昔は見られたものではありませんでした
I rejected the way of the sword and spent all night and day in the town playing shougi.
剣の修行を怠り　村で将棋遊びに明け暮れていました
先代とは そのことでよくケンカをしたものです
My behavior caused many fights between the previous head and myself.
あっ　とがめが　あんたは将棋も強いって褒めてたぞ
Oh, Togame said you're very good at it.
Not at all.
いえ　とんでもない
七花殿は将棋は
Do you play shougi?
I don't have a clue about it.
いや　俺はさっぱり
When my grandfather died, I had to leave behind my life of shougi.
しかし　祖父が亡くなり
わたしも将棋三昧の生活をしているわけにはいかなくなったのです
Succeeding a dojo with no students had no appeal to me,
門下生が一人もいない道場を継ぐことに
わたしは何の魅力も感じませんでしたが
しかし　当主の証であるこの王刀を手にした途端
but the instant I took up the inheritance of Outou, my body became tense.
身が引き締まるような  そんな気分になりました
That's the best I can describe it.
If it's true that I've become a more upright person since that time, then I can say it is all due to this sword, Outou Nokogiri.
もしもわたしがあのころに比べて
少しでもましな人間になっているとするならば
それはこの　「王刀·鋸」のおかげだと思います
Come to think of it, my grandfather also mentioned that he felt like he was reborn when he first took up Outou himself.
そういえば　祖父も先代から王刀を受け継いだ際
生まれ変わったような気持ちになったということでしたが
「王刀·楽土」などと言っていましたね
He called the feeling "Outou Rakudo".
TL note: King's Paradise
Outou Rakudo...
「王刀·楽土」
If Tsuruga Meisai had known about this sword, she'd have done anything to get a hold of it.
敦賀迷彩が知ったら
どうしたって手に入れたかった刀だろうな
Who is Tsuruga Meisai?
敦賀迷彩とは どなたです
いや　何でもない
Ah, never mind.
けどまあ　もしあんたがその木刀のおかげで更生できたっていうなら
Well, if you really were reformed because of that sword, there's not much more you could have hoped for.
それに越したことはないだろうな
どうですかね わたしはどうにも俗物ですから
I wonder.
In the end I am a worldly person.
いや　あんたが俗物なんて ない ない
No, there's no way you're worldly.
You live your life honestly and earnestly.
真っすぐにまじめに生きてるって気がする
Not a single day passes when I don't think about the other life I might have had.
私にも別の人生があったかもしれないと考えない日はありません
別の人生
Other life?
恋に生きる人生もあったでしょう
You must know of a life of love, right?
When I see you and Togame-dono, I cannot stop that feeling which I threw away from welling up inside me.
とがめ殿と七花殿を見ていると
そういったあきらめていた感情が沸き上がってくるの
抑えることができません
But there's nothing wrong with following the way of the sword.
剣の道だって悪くはないだろう
But what can swords accomplish in this age?
しかし　この時代に剣の腕が何になりますか
I am certain that Shinou Issou will die along with me.
心王一鞘流も　おそらくわたしの代で最後になるでしょう
That is why I hold true to my determination to become a swordsman worthy of my ancestors.
なればこそ
先達に恥じぬ剣士たろうという気持ちに偽りありません とはいえ
That said, I'm always clinging onto this idea that I will be the last generation,
わたしの代で終わってしまうものにこうしてしがみつくことは
あるいは　ただの未練なのではないかと思わなくもないのです
but it's crossed my mind that it might just be a lingering affection.
俺も　そうか
Sometimes I also thi—
どうかされましたか 七花殿
What's the matter, Shichika-dono?
いや　いいんじゃないかって思ってさ
Well, maybe it's a good thing.
Killing schools aside, Shinou Issou is a way of life, right?
殺人剣ならまだしも 心王一鞘流っていうのは活人剣なんだろう
It must have a place somewhere in this age of world peace.
この天下太平の時代ってやつにも　そぐわなくはないはずだ
Shichika-dono.
七花殿
たとえ木刀でも　頭を打てば人は死にますよ
Even though this is a practice sword, it will kill if it strikes a person's head.
If it strikes a hand, it will break bones.
小手を打てば骨が折れるし
If it hits the torso, it will rupture organs.
胴を打てば内臓が破裂し
のどを突けば気管がつぶれます
If it strikes the throat, it will smash the windpipe.
だから試合となれば防具を着ける必要がある
That's why in matches, armor must be used.
Only, it cannot cut.
ただ斬れないというだけで
殺人剣でないというだけで
I wield a way of life only in name.
In reality it deals death as much as any other.
活人剣も立派な殺人術なのです
Come, let us continue your training.
さあ　稽古の続きを始めましょう
Sign: Owari
That unpleasant woman...
まあ　あの不愉快な女
It seems her strength as a strategian is the strength to affirm.
奇策士の強さっていうのは肯定する強さなのよね
That strength to affirm everything from her own weaknesses to the ugliness of the world is definitely a threat to me.
何もかもを肯定しようという己の弱さも
この世の醜さも全てのみ込んで肯定しようという
あの女の強さは確かにわたしにとって脅威よ
Which is why I denied her.
だからわたしはあの女を否定した
Judging from the results though, I look like I'm always on the losing end.
けれど結果からみればわたしはこれまであの女に負けっ放しなのよね
You suffer the same losses each time, so this isn't an unfamiliar problem to you, right?
あんたもそのたびに同じ被害に遭ってるんだから人事じゃないでしょ
Well, no matter how many times I'm defeated,
まあ　わたしもわたしで何度蹴落とされても
I raise myself to the same position anyway.
結局は同じ位置に戻ってきちゃうんだけどね
Conversely, you could say that's a weakness of hers.
逆に言えばそういうところに甘さを残している女なのよね
Though I suppose you could say that's an expression of her strength.
それは確かにあの女の肯定力の表れだと思うけど
違う　もっと根本的なことなのかもしれない
No.
It might be something more fundamental than that.
If a strategian is one who makes schemes, then maybe that's all they can do.
策を練るのが策士ならば
奇策しか練らないのが奇策士
あの女は考えることにたけていると同時に
While she excels at thinking, maybe she also excels at not thinking about things...
考えないことにもたけているのかもしれないわ
Hey Emonzaemon,
ねえ　右衛門左衛門
いずれにしてもこの刀集めが
at some point in the future, you're going to have to settle things with that woman once and for all.
あの女との長き因縁に決着をつけることになるでしょう
それに　あの女が最後の１本までたどりつくという可能性も
Though the chances of her reaching the last sword are still maybe 50-50.
まあ五分五分かしらね
ねえ　ちょっと
Hey, have you been listening to me?
さっきから聞いてるの
Oh, right...
あっ　そうだった
あいつ　真庭鳳凰を殺しに行ってるんだった
He's gone off to kill Maniwa Houou...
This is a different beast from the Zettou Kanna that Koumori had.
これは蝙蝠が手にした絶刀鉋とはわけが違う
富士の風穴で
I was shocked when I touched the sword's scabbard with Kawauso's hand back in the Fuji wind caves.
川獺の手でこの刀のさやに触れたときには驚いたものだ
絶刀の特性が 折れず曲がらずよく斬れる
Zettou's focus was how it wouldn't bend or break, and cut easily.
あの頑丈さにあったように
この毒刀鍍の特性は
But Dokutou Mekki's focus is a poison stronger than any other sword.
ほかのどの変体刀よりも強き毒気にあるというのだから
W-W-What's wrong, Houou-sama?
ど　ど　どうされましたか　鳳凰さま
Nothing, I just found it funny.
いや　おかしくなってしまってな
あの奇策士は四季崎記紀の完成形変体刀を８本まで集めているという
That Strategian has collected eight of Shikizaki Kiki's Perfected Deviant Blades,
真庭忍軍にとって絶望的な状況下において
and the Maniwa Corps has been whittled down to this sad state...
And yet, we have managed to obtain the most deviant of the Deviant Blades before she could.
しかし我らの方が先んじて最も変体刀らしい変体刀を入手したというのは
何とも皮肉な話ではないか
Ironic, isn't it?
対等　とまではいかぬまでも
I wouldn't quite call us equal, but with this we have a bargaining chip against the Strategian.
これで　奇策士との駆け引きが可能になろう
B-But, with Umigame-sama's death in Shinano...
し　しかし　信濃に向かっていた海亀さまが落命
Assuming it wasn't Kyotouryuu, there must be another opponent out there...
相手が虚刀流でないとすると　ほかに誰が
もっと　言えば
What do you mean?
どういうこと
Another sword...
もう一つの刀
えっと　えっと
Um... maybe...
He might have been close to Entou Jyuu or Seitou Hakari.
「炎刀·銃」か「誠刀·銓」に近づいていたということでしょうか
U-Um... Houou-sama...
あ　あの　鳳凰さま
「毒刀·鍍」 川獺さまの左腕で読み調べたことで
Did you glean any new information about the other swords when you touched Dokutou Mekki with Kawauso's left hand?
他の刀についての情報が明らかになったりよう
し　しなかったのでしょうか
I haven't yet.
ああ　まだだ
そのためにはさらに深く潜る必要があるよな
To do that I'll have to dive in deeper.
忍法記録たどりはもともとわれの忍法ではない故に
Ninpou: Kiroku Tadori isn't my own ninpou, so I can't say I have a strong command of it yet.
まだ使いこなせているとは言い難い
われの修練しだいだ
I need to master it first.
まずは　海亀が落命したとされる信濃へと足を向けるとするか
I think we should head to where Umigame fell in Shinano for now.
Yes...
はい　海亀さんの　れ　霊も弔わなければ
We should give Umigame a proper burial...
ほかの　亡くなった方たちも
A-And for the o-others as well...
ああっ　すっすみません　蝶々さんのこと
I-I'm sorry!
Chouchou-san is...
いいんだよ
It's fine.
皆の弔いも　必ずするさ
We'll definitely bury them properly.
Y-Yes...
は　はい
では　参るぞ
Let's depart then.
Unallowable.
許さず
You're—
お前は
I cannot allow you to do that, Maniwa Corps soldiers.
その行為を許すわけにはいかない　真庭忍軍の者どもよ
I'm back!
ただいま
Togame, I learned something good today!
いや　とがめ　今日はいい話を聞いたぞ
Cheerio!!
ちぇりお
You've been hitting me for no reason way too much lately...
って最近意味もなく攻撃し過ぎだろ
俺何かしたか
Did I do something?
No reason?!
意味もなく　何を言っておる
What are you talking about?
You think there's no meaning to that punishment?
その鉄ついを受ける意味がないと
Shichika! Sit here!
七花　ちょっとここへ座れ
Aren't you ashamed?
情けないからであろう
You're putting way too much into this Shinou Issou training!
そなた　心王一鞘流の修行になじみ過ぎてないか
Don't you have any pride as the Kyotouryuu head?
虚刀流当主としての矜持はどうした
I really don't want to hear that from the person who told me to do this...
いや　やらせてるあんたに言われたくないんだけど
As a side note, you can jump pretty well with such heavy clothes.
ていうか　よくそんな重たそうな服を着て跳べるよな
髪が短くなった分　身軽になった
I've become more nimble after my hair was cut.
I could probably reach the sky now.
今なら　空も飛べそうだぞ
Eh?
Never mind that!
そんなことはどうでもよい
大体そなた　あの汽口とやけに意気投合しているではないか
You're getting along rather well with that Kiguchi, aren't you.
ああ　そうだな
Yeah, I am.
You admit it?
ええ　認めるのか
Kiguchi's your opponent, you know!
あのな　汽口は戦う相手だぞ
Well, see...
いやね　心王一鞘流と虚刀流 互いに忘れられた流派だとか
Shinou Issou and Kyotouryuu are both forgotten schools, and we both became heads recently so—
同じように最近当主になったとか
色々
Kiiii!
"Kiiii"?
ふーんだ　残念だけどそんな楽しい修行生活ももう終わりだ
Nyaaa!
I'm afraid that your fun training times are over!
I'm ending it!
終わらせてやるもんね
Huh?
Well, it took me way longer than I'd have thought possible, but I've come up with one!
まあ　思わぬ時間がかかってしまったが
取りあえず　思い付いたぞ
思い付いたって　何が
Come up with... what?
A scheme, of course!
奇策に決まっておる
とにかく色々考えてみたのだが
I thought about it for a while, and I came to the conclusion that there is only one real way for you to beat Kiguchi Zanki in a fight!
そなたが汽口慚愧に勝つための現実的なやり方は
この一つしかなさそうだ
There's only one way I can beat Kiguchi?
俺が汽口に勝つ方法は一つしかねえのかよ
And with a training sword, armor, and match regulations too!
むろん　木刀使用防具着用規則採用という条件下でのことだ
そなたがまっとうにはだしで手っ甲を外した
If you were allowed to fight her barehanded without any shirt, I'm confident you could beat her,
上半身裸の状態であの女と戦えば
きっとそなたが勝つともちろんわたしは信じておる
しかし　汽口の性格上それは不可能であろう
but there's no way Kiguchi would allow that.
There's no way?
不可能か
それで　俺があいつに勝つための奇策っていうのは
So what's the scheme you have for me to beat her?
そなたのその弱さを利用する
We're going to use that very weakness of yours.
弱さ
Weakness?
You haven't forgotten your fight with Itezura Konayuki on Mt. Odori, right?
踊山においての凍空こなゆき戦をそなたは忘れておらぬだろう
この刀集めの旅におけるそなたの最初の敗北
It was your first defeat throughout our whole journey.
ああ そりゃ忘れるわけがないよ
Yeah... I couldn't forget that...
We're going to do likewise.
あれを踏襲する
踏襲
Likewise?
Maybe I should put it in a different way.
踏襲というより　ここではこう言っておいた方がいいか
わたしたちが狙うのは まぐれ勝ちだ
We're aiming to win by fluke!
Unfathomable.
分からず
I didn't think those two would just escape and leave you behind.
まさか　お前が残って２人を逃がすとは
煙幕か　古臭い忍法を使うな
A smokescreen...
Quite an antiquated ninpou you used.
Shut up.
うるさいのよ
All it means is that I'm more than enough to take you on by myself.
ただ単にあんたごときはわたし一人で十分というだけのことよ
Quite the confidence.
大した自信だ
しかしわたしはお前が相手では不満なのだ
However, I am not content to have you as an opponent.
わたしの目的は真庭鳳凰の暗殺なのだから
My objective is to assassinate Maniwa Houou.
あんた　何者よ
Who are you?
Unanswerable.
答えず
Might you be the one who killed Umigame-san?
もしかして　あんただね
海亀さんをやったのは
あれは「毒刀·鍍」か
Is that Dokutou Mekki?
Oh, so you heard us talking?
あ　何だい　あんた話を聞いていたのかい
You've got good hearing at such a distance.
あの距離からよく聞こえたねえ
No, I already knew.
いや　知っていただけだ
What?
You need not understand, for you will die here anyway.
理解しなくていい　どうせお前はここで死ぬのだから
Is that so?
そうかい
むちか
Whips?
Maniwa Ninpou: Eigouben!
TL note: Infinite whips
真庭忍法　永劫鞭
Maniwa Ninpou: Eigouben
Here I come!
行くわよ
"Mandarin Duck the Rewind" Oshidori, huh...
巻き戻しの鴛鴦　か
どうする
What now?
面白い
Interesting.
I'm flattered by your praise.
褒めてもらってうれしいわね
In return, let me teach you something.
お礼に教えてあげる
これ　攻撃力はそれほどでもないの
This doesn't actually have that much striking power.
If you watch out for the blades on the ends, you can avoid any fatal injury.
先端の刃物だけ気を付けていれば致命傷は避けられるわよ
However,
でもね　この永劫鞭は
even so, Eigouben will slowly torture you to death.
敵をじわじわとなぶり殺しにするのに最高に適した武器なのよ
It's the perfect weapon for me!
In that case...
ならば　相生拳法　背弄拳
Aioi Kenpo: Hairouken
Note: Rear Trickery Fist
I'm sorry, but...
悪いわね
Unbelievable.
禁じ得ず
I am truly shocked.
驚きを禁じ得ない　背弄拳が通じないとは
For Hairouken not to have worked...
そんな相手は真庭鳳凰くらいかと
I thought Maniwa Houou was the only one in that class.
はあ　何だい　あんた鳳凰さまと知り合いなのかい
Oh? Do you and Houou-sama know each other?
He's more than just an acquaintance, but not quite a sworn enemy.
知り合い以上　怨敵未満だ
You didn't answer the question!
答えになってないよ
What's wrong?
どうしたのもう終わりかい
Is that all?
そうよね　これはむちの結界
It is, right?
This is my whip's barrier.
As a defense, it serves as the best offense.
防御こそ　最大の攻撃ってこと
じゃ　こっちから終わらせてあげる
Allow me to finish this then.
あんたの命　海亀さんに捧げてやる
I will offer your life as a sacrifice to Umigame-san.
だが　それはわたしには通じず
I'm afraid that will be ineffective.
What... is that...
それは　何
Discontent.
満たず
結局真庭鳳凰暗殺は　失敗だ
In the end, I failed to assassinate Maniwa Houou.
Though, this woman did well in carrying out her duty.
しかしこの女は見事に役割を全うした
さすがは忍者
A true ninja.
忍者を辞めたわたしより ずっと潔い
You are far more honorable than someone like me who left the ninja ways.
褒めてやろう
You have my respect.
Unlistening.
聞こえず　か
蝶　ちょう　さん
Chou...chou...san...
Hey, if possible I'd like to avoid a dirty fight with Kiguchi.
あのさ　できれば汽口とは泥仕合は避けたいな
S-So you really have f-fallen for her!
やはりそなた　汽口にじょ 情が移ったのだな
Have you changed your heart yet again?!
そなたまたも心変わりをしたというのか
"Again"? When have I—
またもって　俺がいつ
I know what the two of you were doing together in the dojo!
ど　道場で
二人きりで何をしておったのかわたしは知っているのだぞ
Right, training, as you know...
ああ　知ってのとおり　稽古だ
Yeah, what kind of training I wonder!
何の稽古だか
What?
I even put my faith in you and persuaded you to go!
わたしはそなたを信頼してあの道場に通わせていたというのに
Dammit, I can't bear your erratic nature any more!
もうそなたの浮気性には付き合いきれぬわ
I'm the one who can't bear you!
付き合いきれないのはこっちだ
自分からそういう話を振ってきておいて
You're always the one who brings up this subject.
俺はあんたの言うとおり　この十日間
These past ten days, I've done just as you said—
とがめ ちょっとヤバいかもしれないぞ
Togame, this might be bad.
"Bad"?
ヤバい
いや　まあ確かに　よその流派の門下生になれという
Well, it's true that my order for you to study at that school as a student might have been unfair,
わたしの命令は理不尽であったと思うし
and maybe that drove you away from me, but I had my reasons!
それで愛想を尽かされても仕方ないのかもしれないけど
わたしにはわたしなりの考えがあってだな
You could have just asked me about it!
それを聞いてくれてもいいではないか
You could have!
それを　それを
分かった　分かった
I get it, I get it.
That discussion is already over.
いや　その件についての話はもう終わっている
「終わっている」とは何だ
What's over?!
まだ話し合いの余地は残っておるだろうが
There's still more to talk about!
２人で築いてきた関係を
How can you end the relationship we've built up together in such a one-sided manner?!
１人で一方的に終わらそうとはどういうつもりだ
How do you think I've felt these past ten days...
わたしはこの十日間どういう思いで
No, I mean what's bad is your scheme.
いや　ヤバいのはとがめの立てた奇策だよ
そうなのか　ならばよい
Really?
That's fine then.
No, it really isn't...
いやよくはないだろ
So what's wrong with my scheme?
で　奇策がどうヤバい
つまりさ　その奇策は
Basically, you're relying on the premise that I'm a complete amateur at using swords, right?
俺が刀剣使いの素人であることを前提に考えられているわけだろ
けれどとがめ 十日前ならいざ知らず
I don't know about before ten days ago, but in the time you came up with that scheme,
あんたがその奇策を練っている間に
俺は達人である汽口から直々にずっと教えを受けていたんだぜ
I've been receiving direct training the whole time from Kiguchi, a master.
俺はもう素人とは言えないんじゃないのか
At this point you can't really call me an amateur anymore, right?
I see...
あっそうか 確かにそこまでは考えてはいなかった
I didn't take that into consideration.
That was a mistake on my part.
わたしとしたことが不覚だったな
Okay, fine.
よし　分かった
Kiss.
Do you still remember anything?
まだ何か覚えておるか
全部忘れた
I've forgotten it all.
まだ七花殿は　わたしと戦うまでには及んでいないと
Shichika-dono is still not at a level to be competing against me!
相手の実力が劣るという理由で立ち合うに及ばないとは
Don't you think it's rather conceited to claim that your opponent is not skilled enough to be a worthy fight?
汽口殿もずいぶんと思い上がったことを言うではないか
That's not at all like the way of the sword.
剣の道にさような絶対はあるまい
No matter what the difference in skill is, once you take up your sword and face each other, you are equals.
どのような実力差があろうが
剣を取って立ち合う以上は対等であろう
分かりました
Understood.
Okay.
とがめの思惑どおりだ
That went exactly as Togame planned...
ただ　その前にお願いがあります
However, I have a request before that.
この勝負 わたしが勝ったならば
If I win this fight,
どうか「王刀·鋸」をすっぱりとあきらめていただきたい
I'd like you to give up entirely on Outou Nokogiri.
Agreed.
承知した
We'll begin with best of 9 shougi then.
ではまずは将棋戦９局
王手
Checkmate.
ですが　結局４勝５敗
However the score is 4 to 5.
You win the best of 9.
将棋戦９局はとがめ殿の勝ちです
では次 剣術は１回勝負の１本勝負で
Then next is the one round, one game swordsmanship match.
Are you ready, Shichika-dono?
用意はいいですか七花殿
いいよ
Yes.
一応先に言っとくけど 十日間色々と世話になったな
I just want to say before we start that you've taught me a lot these past ten days.
I was a terrible student who couldn't even take baby steps, but I feel it was a good experience.
何一つ身に付きはしなかった
出来の悪い門下生だったけれど
いい経験になったと思っているぜ
No,
いや　わたしの方が多くのものを学ばされました
I learned far more from the experience.
おそらく
I most likely still don't have the qualifications to teach anything.
まだ私は人にものを教えられるような立場にない
ということだったのでしょう
かのような結果に終わってしまったことについては
I am truly sorry that I could not provide better results for you in the end.
誠に申し訳なく思っております
Don't apologize yet.
まだ謝るなよ
If I'm able to beat you here, it'll actually be proof of your worth, right?
これでもしも俺があんたに勝てば
あんたの正しさが逆に証明されるってことにもなるんじゃないか
そうですね
I suppose.
七花殿　あの
Shichika-dono...
Um...
木刀の持ち方が　間違っています
You're holding your sword incorrectly.
Oh, right.
Shichika-dono.
七花殿　心の鬼を心で斬る
Slay your heart's demon with your heart.
From this comes the name Zanki.
これをもって慚愧と名乗る
心王一鞘流十二代目 汽口慚愧 お手並み拝見いたします
I am the 12th generation Shinou Issou head, Kiguchi Zanki.
Demonstrate your skills before me.
言われなくても見せてやるさ
I would without being told.
However, by that point you might be torn into pieces.
ただしそのころには
あんたは八つ裂きになっているかもしれないけどな
Then let us begin.
それではそろそろ始めましょうか
Then let the match begin!
それではいざ尋常に　始め
Pawn to 6,7.
７六歩
I reply with pawn 3,4.
わたしは３四歩と返す
Pawn 2,6.
２六歩
Pawn 4,4.
４四歩
Pawn 2,5.
２五歩
Bishop 3,3.
３三角
It's almost as if she's reading what moves I'm making...
まるでわたしの手を読み知っているかのように
Gold 4,8.
４八銀
I can't move...
動けない　駄目だ集中力を乱される
Not good, she's throwing off my concentration...
３二銀
Gold 3,2.
５六歩
Pawn 5,6.
I see.
そうか　だから９局対局を負けで終わらせたのか
That's why she lost the 9th game...
Gold 4,3.
４三銀
It was so she would have the first move...
最後に先手を取るために
５八金　右
Gold 5,8.
I've only played 10 games with her,
この人とは１０局対局しただけ
わずか２０００手でわたしの動きを読み取ってしまった
and yet in only 2000 moves, she learned my exact play style...
Pawn 5,5.
この人は
King 6,8.
６八玉
I just have to stop thinking about it.
考えなければいいのだ
I see...
そうか　七花殿は将棋ができないのであったな
Silver 6,7.
Shichika-dono doesn't know how to play shougi...
７八銀
Gold 7,8.
I should just stop thinking, but I can't help myself!
考えなければいいのに
どうしても考えてしまう
Gold 5,8.
Silver 7,7.
Rook 2,2.
２二飛
７八玉
King 7,8.
Head Strike!
面
Woah!
The first match between the Shinou Issou school and the blade-wielding Kyotouryuu was incredibly quiet and anticlimactic.
心王一鞘流対虚刀流の一番は とても静かにあっけなく
Even so, the match was decided.
しかも　地味に決着がついたのでございます
I see, psychological warfare...
なるほど　心理戦ね
まったく俺の苦手な領域だな
That's definitely an area I'm terrible at.
しかしとがめのその才覚は
I kind of wish you'd have shown that genius against Tsuruga Meisai too.
できれば敦賀迷彩戦あたりで発揮してほしかったものだが
Fool.
たわけが だから何度も言うが
I keep telling you, battles are by nature your domain of experience.
戦闘はあくまでそなたの領分であろうが
今回のことこそ例外だと思え
This time was just an exception.
Well, I guess...
まあそうだな でもさ　あれって厳密には反則じゃないのか
But isn't what you did technically foul play?
Talking to the contestants from the sidelines seems unfair to me...
横合いから選手にぺらぺらと話し掛けるっていうのは
何だかずるい気もするんだけど
そなたは何を言っておるのだ
What are you talking about?
反則に決まっておろうが
Of course it was foul play.
でも　だったらそう指摘しそうなものじゃねえか
Wouldn't Kiguchi have objected then?
You'd think so, given how strict she normally is...
あれだけ規則にうるさい汽口なら
But think, Shichika.
だがな七花 その反則を取るのは誰だ
Who was it who broke the rules?
The referee—me!
審判役のわたしであろうが
確かに
I guess...
And in that town of all places, there's no way anyone would call foul on talking about shougi.
それに　この村において
まさか将棋を指したことを反則扱いはできまいよ
なぜならここは　将棋の聖地だふん
That's the holy land for shougi, after all.
Your shougi was really amazing, though.
でも　とがめの将棋はホントにすごいな
全力でお願いします
Please don't hold back.
In the blink of an eye...
あっという間に
In 42 moves.
４２手だ
I lose.
参りました
It was an overwhelming victory for you.
とがめの圧勝
You also won overwhelmingly despite being restricted to fighting at 60% strength at one point.
そなたも６割の力で戦うという縛りでも圧勝したではないか
No no, I just barely won after using Hyakka Ryouran.
奥義·百花繚乱を繰り出して　やっとの勝利だ
参りました
I lose.
I underestimated you, Shichika-dono.
おみそれしました　七花殿
Please forgive my rudeness in treating someone with your skill as a student to such a novice as I.
知らなかったとはいえ
あなたのような使い手を
わたしのごとき未熟者の門下生として扱った無礼を
お許しください
I said you don't need to apologize.
だから　そんなに謝んなよ
あんたの剣は 何も間違っちゃいないんだから
There was nothing wrong with your swordsmanship.
Becoming weaker when wielding a sword is almost like a curse.
剣を取った方が弱くなるなど まるで呪いのようですね
呪い
Curse...
Here.
どうぞ　約束どおり「王刀·鋸」はお渡しします
As promised, I shall hand Outou Nokogiri to you.
いいのかよ それは当主の証しなんだろ
Are you sure?
Isn't that the proof that you're the school's head?
It seems I am no longer qualified to hold this sword.
わたしにはまだ　この刀を持つ資格はないようです
No, on the contrary...
いえ　逆ですね
わたしは　この刀からすでに十分な力を得ました
I've obtained more than enough strength from this sword.
天下国家のために使うなり折って捨てるなり　何なりと
Whether you'll use it for the greater good of the country or just throw it away, I leave it in your hands.
その後の処理はお任せいたします
Please visit again sometime.
またいつでもいらしてください
When you do, I would be honored to face you again.
そしてその際には ぜひもう一度お相手願いたい
そのときを楽しみに
Until then, I will look forward to your coming, and continue to watch over the Shinou Issou school's legacy.
わたしは心王一鞘流の看板を これからも守り続けようと思います
Legacy?
看板って　看板は王刀じゃなかったのかよ
Isn't Outou the legacy?
Slay your heart's demon with your heart.
心の鬼を心で斬る
これをもって　慚愧と名乗る
From this comes the name Zanki.
Henceforth, I myself will be the proof.
これからはわたし自身が看板です
I'll be the showgirl!
TL Note: Pun on legacy - kanban → kanban musume - showgirl
看板娘です
楽しかったな
It was fun.
Cheerio!
ちぇりお
What's with that smile on your face?
何だ　鼻の下が伸びておるぞ
どこが
What smile?
Oh, now you're conscious of it?
おっ　自覚ありか
What do you mean?
だから　何の
Well, whatever.
まあよい それより残る刀はいよいよ３本か
Anyway, there are only three swords left.
I wonder if the Maniwani have been collecting them while we were out and about.
まにわにの連中 あっちもあっちで刀集めてたりするのかな
I wonder.
さて　どうだろうな
連中にそれだけの器量があるとも思えぬが
I'm not incredibly impressed by their skills, but it wouldn't surprise me if they'd gotten a hold of one at this point.
１本くらいはやつらの手に落ちていても不思議はないな
Shichika...
七花 今回の件はあまり考えたくない今後の可能性を示唆しておるな
What we learned this time implies a possibility about what lies ahead that I don't really want to think about.
Oh, you mean that I might get weaker by trying to use a sword?
ああ　俺が刀を持つとめちゃめちゃ弱いってことか
けど　今回みたいな場合ってさすがにもうないと
I doubt I'll ever get a chance to do that again though.
Well, while that is worrisome, I was referring to General Kyuu.
いや　それはそれではなはだ不安要素ではあるが
旧将軍のことだ
General Kyuu?
旧将軍
The sword hunt.
刀狩令のことだ
Why wasn't he able to get a hold of Outou Nokogiri?
旧将軍は「どうして「王刀·鋸」を収集できなかったのか」とな
Why?
どうしてって
Setting aside that it didn't give off poison, or that maybe it removes poison,
毒を発さないとか毒気を抜くとか
そんな王刀楽土の効果をさておけば
Besides those "King's paradise" effects, it was just a training sword.
あくまでもただの木刀だぞ
その木刀で
How was its owner able to repulse General Kyuu's armies back then?
どうやって当時の「王刀·鋸」の所有者は旧将軍を撃退したのだ
The sword hunt...
刀狩令 表向きの目的は 刀大仏建立のため
Its official purpose was to build the Sword Buddha.
裏向きの目的は剣客撲滅のため
Its hidden purpose was to eliminate all the swordsmen.
Its true purpose was to collect all of Shikizaki Kiki's Deviant Blades.
真の目的は四季崎記紀の変体刀集め
しかし実は　その裏があったのではないだろうか
But I wonder if perhaps there was another hidden purpose.
旧将軍の刀集めの失敗も
It's possible that General Kyuu failed for reasons other than what I originally thought.
わたしが思うところとは違ったのかもしれぬ
だとしたら　どうなるんだ
So what would that mean?
Then... that would mean...
だから
だとしたら
No, it's still just a possibility.
いや　まだ可能性の話だ
そなたが気にするようなことではない 忘れておけ
You needn't worry about it.
Forget it.
Forget it?
「忘れておけ」って でもそんな気になること言われたら
You can't just tell me something that interesting then say that...
Or what, do you...
それとも何か また
Do you want me to make you forget again?
また忘れさせてほしいというおねだりのつもりか
Oh?
What's wrong, Shichika?
After this, the two made a brief stop at Owari and quickly moved onto their next objective.
さて　２人はこの後いったん尾張に戻ったものの
せきたてられるように
次の目的地へと旅立つことになるのでございます
Their 10th target is Seitou Hakari.
１０本目の収集対象は　「誠刀·銓」
And the land they're headed to is Oushuu.
そして次の目的地といえば 奥州
The story is reaching its climax.
物語も佳境に入ってまいりました
We shall see Togame's hidden birthplace, the land where the next Perfected Deviant Blade, Seitou Hakari resides.
あろうことか
奇策士とがめの知られざる生まれ故郷が
次の完成形変体刀　「誠刀·銓」の在りかなのでございます
およそ２０年ぶりに 里帰りを果たすことになる
It will have been about 20 years since she visited her parents.
And on that note,
といったところで
『刀語』 今月こよいのお楽しみはここまでにございます
the story of Katanagatari on this month and this evening ends here.
kumori naki sono hamon yadori shi kedakasa wo mitomu
Thou who wields this unclouded blade, I behold witness to thine honor
uchi naru mi ni mamiete moyu
The sacred flame of thy dharma body
taezu nagareru tomadoi mayoi wo furiharaishi toki
Whence thou shrug the endless running confusion and hesitation,
tsumi ete nasu iyashiki oi
Build sins, end in vulgar ancience,
tagaeru ishi wo miokuri
Bid farewell to a lying, dying wish
曇り凪ぎそろう 刃紋やどりし
ayumi ga koto koto naredo
The steps echo
気高さをみとむ
内なる身に まみえて燃ゆ
tooku
Far away,
絶えず流れる惑い迷いを　振り払いし時
mukau tabiji sono hate wa
My journey, what lies beyond
Deep,
fukaku
My spirit, this silence
waga kokoro kono shizukesa
潰えてなす　卑しき檻
tsuyoku
Strong,
違える意志を見送り
togisumasareta inochi ga
Sharpened, life
waga akashi
I was
歩みが 異異なれど
Damn that Shichika!
I take my eyes off him for a second, and he's already looking at another woman!
遠く
Geez!
I guess he prefferes women with long hair.
遠く旅路　その果ては
Now then, our next destination is Oushuu - Hyakkeijou.
深く
The owner of the sword is Higaki Rinne, who's 350 years old.
深く心を凝る静けさ
"Take it during the battle"?
強く
I don't understand what Sen-nii was thinking.
Just what is this guy thinking and planning?
研ぎ澄まされた命は
Next time on Katanagatari: Seitou Hakari
我が証
Seitou
Hakari
Scales
the True
Cheerio!